Guide to the Harry A. Siitonen Papers, 1926-1990, bulk 1953-1977 RL.11182
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Harry A. Siitonen papers
1926-1990 and undated, bulk 1953-1977
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Siitonen, Harry A.
RL.11182
8.0 Linear Feet
The Harry A. Siitonen papers document Siitonen's work with the Socialist movement on the national and local scale in the 1950s through the 1970s. Siitonen, an alum of Michigan State University and son of Finnish immigrants, was heavily involved in the Socialist Party USA through the mid 1970s. He was chair of the Los Angeles and San Francisco Locals of the Socialist Party-USA during the 1950s-1970s, and active in the national Social Party-USA committee after its reconstitution in the 1970s. The papers are arranged into the following series: Correspondence, Subject Files, Party Conventions, Regional and National Organizations, Socialist Party Action Committee, California Socialist Parties, and Printed Materials. The papers include incoming and outgoing correspondence, internal memos, meeting minutes, resolutions, position papers, constitutions, and other records of party activities at local, state, and national levels.
Arrangement
Arranged into series: Correspondence, Subject Files, Party Conventions, Regional and National Organizations, Socialist Party Action Committee, California Socialist Parties, Printed Materials.
Biographical / Historical
Born March 18, 1926, in Worcester, Massachusetts, Harry A. Siitonen is alum of Michigan State University, retired newspaper printer, writer for Finnish-American periodicals, and actor. Sittonen's parents immigrated to the United States from Finland in 1915, both of whom were stalwart members of the Finnish Federation. He joined the Communist Party while at Michigan State, and later joined the Socialist Party USA. He was chair of the Los Angeles and San Francisco Locals of the Socialist Party-USA during the 1950s-1970s, and active in the national Social Party-USA committee after its reconstitution in the 1970s. He resigned from the Socialist Party USA in 1976, citing disillusionment and refocusing his efforts on the Industrial Workers of the World. He lives in the San Francisco Bay Area.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Harry Siitonen Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1996.
Related Materials
Rubenstein Library also holds the Socialist Party Papers.
Collection Overview
The Harry A. Siitonen papers document Siitonen's work with the Socialist movement on the national and local scale in the 1950s through the 1970s. Siitonen, alum of Michigan State University and son of Finnish immigrants, was heavily involved in the Socialist Party USA from the 1950s until 1976, at which time he broke from the party citing disillusionment. He thereafter refocused his efforts on the Industrial Workers of the World. The collection consists of party documents from his time with the Socialist Party USA including: internal memos, meeting minutes, resolutions, position papers, convention handouts, notes, as well as incoming and outgoing correspondence and subject files.
Socialist parties -- United States; Socialism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Radicalism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Political activists -- United States -- Correspondence; Socialists -- United States -- Correspondence; Siitonen, Harry A.; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Democratic Socialist Federation (U.S.); Harrington, Michael, 1928-; San Francisco Socialist Coalition; Socialist Party of California
- Correspondence, 1957-1990 and undated; 1
  - Correspondence, 1957-1990 and undated; 38 folders (Box 1)
- Subject Files, 1926-1972 and undated; 2
  - Bibliographies, book lists-test, 1965 and undated (Box 2)
  - Book reviews (Box 2)
  - Clippings 1 of 2 (Box 2)
  - Clippings 2 of 2 (Box 2)
  - Ephemera, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Flyers (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Position statements and and other writings, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Siitonen Campaign papers (Box 2)
  - Socialist Party History (1 of 2), 1952-1971 (Box 2)
  - Socialist Party History (2 of 2), 1948-1969 (Box 2)
  - Socialist Party USA Siitonen's resignation, 1926 (Box 2)
  - Socialist thought, 1952-1972 and undated (Box 2)
  - Socialist Party - Personal Inc. letter from Upton Sinclair and ephemera, 1953-1971 (Box 2)
  - Writings (Box 2)
  - Writings by/about Michael Harrington, 1971-1972 and undated (Box 2)
- Party Conventions, 1958-1977 and undated; 3
  - Socialist Party - Democratic Socialist Federation convention, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party - Social Democratic Federation, 1958-1967 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party - Social Democratic Federation Convention, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party - SDF Convention, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party National Convention, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party USA Convention, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party Convention, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party, USA Convention, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party, USA Convention - newsclippings, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party - Democratic Socialist Federation unity referendum, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party USA pre-conference correspondence, January - June 1973; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party, USA Convention, Mar-Jun 1973 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party Convention minutes, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party National Convention, convention documents, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party USA National Convention, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party Convention Constitution, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party National Convention, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party USA National Convention, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party USA Platform, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party Convention, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Socialist Party USA Positions (Box 3)
- Regional and National Organizations, 1954-1973 and undated; 4
  - Committee for a Socialist Program, 1954-1957 (Box 4)
  - Debs Caucus, 1968-1972 and undated; 6 folders (Box 4)
  - People's Party, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Socialist Party of Ill. (Box 4)
  - Socialist Party of Milwaukee, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Socialist Party of NC, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Socialist Party of Wisconsin, 1968-1971 (Box 4)
  - Union for Democratic Socialism, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Young People's Socialist League, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Young People's Socialist League Convention, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
- Socialist Party National Action Committee, 1959-1975 and undated; 5
  - Socialist Party, USA National Action Committee, 1959-1966 (Box 4)
  - Socialist Party, USA National Action Committee, 1967-1975 and undated; 12 folders (Box 4)
- California Socialist Parties, 1954-1973 and undated
- Printed Material, 1919-1979 and undated
  - The Illinois Comrade, 1919 (Box 5)
  - Independent Socialist Committee, 1968-1972 (Box 5)